<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugs.ecmascript.org/page.cgi?id=bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="4.4.4+"
          urlbase="https://bugs.ecmascript.org/"
          
          maintainer="dherman@mozilla.com"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>123</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2011-07-08 08:37:00 -0700</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Spec is confusing on what constitutes unicode whitespace</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2015-10-14 17:33:28 -0700</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>ECMA-262, Editions 5 and 5.1</product>
          <component>technical content</component>
          <version>Edition 5.1</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>RESOLVED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc></bug_file_loc>
          <status_whiteboard></status_whiteboard>
          <keywords></keywords>
          <priority>Normal</priority>
          <bug_severity>trivial</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>---</target_milestone>
          
          <blocked>156</blocked>
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Dave Fugate">dfugate</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Allen Wirfs-Brock">allen</assigned_to>
          <cc>brterlso</cc>
    
    <cc>mathias</cc>
          

      

      

      

          <comment_sort_order>oldest_to_newest</comment_sort_order>  
          <long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>285</commentid>
    <comment_count>0</comment_count>
    <who name="Dave Fugate">dfugate</who>
    <bug_when>2011-07-08 08:37:51 -0700</bug_when>
    <thetext>Section 7.2 of ES5.1 contains Table 2 which lists out all valid whitespace characters.  Note that the unicode character, \u0085, does not fall under any categories of this table. \u0085 is &quot;NEXT LINE&quot; and is referred to generically as a &quot;line break&quot; character in the Unicode 3.0 standard - see ftp://ftp.unicode.org/Public/3.0-Update/LineBreak-5.txt.  Also, note that Unicode 3.0 is the version of the standard that ES5.1 &apos;lines&apos; up with as far as character encodings are concerned.

Section 7.3 of ES5.1 contains Table 3 which lists out all valid line terminator characters.  &quot;NEXT LINE&quot; does not full under any of the categories of this table either.  7.3 then goes on to state that:
    Only the characters in Table 3 are treated as line 
    terminators. Other new line or line breaking characters 
    are treated as white space but not as line terminators.


Based on this info, a reasonable person would infer that \u0085, a &quot;line breaking&quot; character as defined by Unicode 3.0, is treated as white space by conforming implementations.  In fact, the JavaScript community documented this exactly at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newline:
    ECMAScript[5] accepts LS and PS as line breaks, but 
    considers U+0085 (NEL) white space, not a line break.
Also, this confused the author of several test262 tests who had assumed \u0085 was considered white space.


ES5.2/ES6 should clarify this situation by changing the text in section 7.3 to be something like:
    Only the characters in Table 3 are treated as line 
    terminators. Other new line or line breaking characters 
    are treated as white space but not as line terminators.  Note 
    however that being treated as white space in this case is not
    the same as being added to Table 2.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>14801</commentid>
    <comment_count>1</comment_count>
    <who name="Brian Terlson">brterlso</who>
    <bug_when>2015-10-14 17:33:28 -0700</bug_when>
    <thetext>It looks like this text got cleaned up in ES2015. I find the current text to be more than acceptable.</thetext>
  </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>