<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugs.ecmascript.org/page.cgi?id=bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="4.4.4+"
          urlbase="https://bugs.ecmascript.org/"
          
          maintainer="dherman@mozilla.com"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>2836</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2014-05-10 12:00:00 -0700</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>use of &quot;UTC&quot;</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2015-02-18 14:40:50 -0800</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Draft for 7th Edition</product>
          <component>Deferred from 6th edition</component>
          <version>unspecified</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CONFIRMED</bug_status>
          <resolution></resolution>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc></bug_file_loc>
          <status_whiteboard></status_whiteboard>
          <keywords></keywords>
          <priority>Normal</priority>
          <bug_severity>normal</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>---</target_milestone>
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Michael Dyck">jmdyck</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Allen Wirfs-Brock">allen</assigned_to>
          <cc>claude.pache</cc>
          

      

      

      

          <comment_sort_order>oldest_to_newest</comment_sort_order>  
          <long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>8300</commentid>
    <comment_count>0</comment_count>
    <who name="Michael Dyck">jmdyck</who>
    <bug_when>2014-05-10 12:00:36 -0700</bug_when>
    <thetext>Recapping items 5-8 of Bug 2701:

20.3.2.1 / step 5.a:
20.3.2.2 / step 10.a:
20.3.2.3 / step 14.a:
20.3.2.3 / step 15.a:
These say:
    &quot;... the time value (UTC) identifying the current time.&quot;

[And there are other uses of the term &quot;UTC&quot;.]

--------
I said:

Saying &quot;(UTC)&quot; suggests that a time value is bound to a particular time zone, which it isn&apos;t.

--------
Allen Wirfs-Brock replied:

Saying (UTC) means the exact opposite:  that the time value is a universal time
rather than  a local time associated with a particular time zone. See the
definition of time value in 20.3.1.1.

Removing the &quot;(UTC)&quot; would make these phrases ambiguous WRT whether the
resulting timevalue should be a UTC value or a locally adjusted value.

These particular phrases have been in the ES spec. since the introduction of
Date object.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>8301</commentid>
    <comment_count>1</comment_count>
    <who name="Michael Dyck">jmdyck</who>
    <bug_when>2014-05-10 12:01:46 -0700</bug_when>
    <thetext>&gt; Saying (UTC) means the exact opposite:  that the time value is a universal
&gt; time rather than  a local time associated with a particular time zone.

That appears to be a somewhat wishful interpretation of UTC.

For most people&apos;s purposes, UTC is equivalent to GMT, which is more obviously bound to a time zone.

Also, as 20.3.1.1 makes clear:
    In time values leap seconds are ignored.
    It is assumed that there are exactly 86,400,000 milliseconds per day.
These statements are not true of UTC.


&gt; See the definition of time value in 20.3.1.1.

Yes, in fact, to avoid these concerns, it would be better for the spec to say something like:
    &quot;... the time value (see 20.3.1.1) identifying the current time.&quot;


&gt; Removing the &quot;(UTC)&quot; would make these phrases ambiguous WRT whether the
&gt; resulting timevalue should be a UTC value or a locally adjusted value.

Given how 20.3.1.1 defines &apos;time value&apos;, I don&apos;t think that ambiguity exists. But if you think it does, it would perhaps be better to clarify that in one spot, rather than multiple spots. E.g., maybe add a paragraph to 20.3.1.1 about the meaning of the phrase &quot;a time value identifying the current time&quot;. (Perhaps introduce a shorter term like &quot;the current time value&quot;.)</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>8487</commentid>
    <comment_count>2</comment_count>
    <who name="Claude Pache">claude.pache</who>
    <bug_when>2014-05-15 03:56:40 -0700</bug_when>
    <thetext>There is also the introductory paragraph of Section 20.3.2 (The Date Constructor): 

    &quot;When Date is called as a function rather than as a constructor, it returns a String representing the current time (UTC).&quot; 

The precision &quot;(UTC)&quot;, at least when interpreted non-convolutedly, is contradicted by every implementation I&apos;ve tried, for all of them give me a local time, e.g.: 

    &quot;Thu May 15 2014 09:15:16 GMT+0200 (CEST)&quot;

In order to avoid such a confusion, and similar ones, one should be precise on the vocabulary used.

* On the one hand, the notion of local time, time zone or universal time, and the abbreviation &quot;UTC&quot;, are relevant when a time is expressed as an hour within a given day, e.g: &quot;9.30am&quot;. 
* On the other hand, a number of milliseconds (or days, or whatever) is just expressing a difference between two instants, and is independent to the notion of timezone or UTC. The &quot;millisecond&quot; is a duration completely defined by the International System of Units.

In fact, the spec is itself confused about the term &quot;time value&quot;:

* In Section 20.3.1.1, the technical term &quot;time value&quot; seems to be defined as the number of milliseconds since the Epoch, plus a correction regarding leap seconds. Note that such a number isn&apos;t itself in UTC for any correct meaning of &quot;UTC&quot;, even if some parts of its definition refer more or less implicitly to Universal Coordinated Time, such as the notion of leap second, or the usual definition of the Epoch. 

* Section 20.3.1.6 Week Day (as a random example) gives a formula that computes the &quot;weekday for a particular time value /t/&quot;. But the &quot;time value /t/&quot; used in that formula corresponds precisely to the number of milliseconds since 1st Jan 1970 midnight in a given timezone, in contradiction of the definition of &quot;time value&quot; given in Section 20.3.1.1.

In order to add clarity, one should use the technical term &quot;time value&quot; only exactly as defined in Section 20.3.1.1, rather than adding a spurious (UTC) precision in some cases. For instance, the introductory text of Section 20.3.1.6 could say: &quot;The operator WeekDay calculates a week day from a given number of milliseconds since 1st Jan 1970 midnight in a given timezone .&quot;</thetext>
  </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>